<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle of a Catholique to his friend a Protestant touching the doctrine of reall presence. Or, the answer to a question propounded in these tearms What should move you, contrary to the plain testimony of your senses, to believe, that after consecration the bread and wine in the sacrament is become really Christs very body and blood.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38514</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3164AA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222634</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833783</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833783</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38261</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38514)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38261)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2205:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle of a Catholique to his friend a Protestant touching the doctrine of reall presence. Or, the answer to a question propounded in these tearms What should move you, contrary to the plain testimony of your senses, to believe, that after consecration the bread and wine in the sacrament is become really Christs very body and blood.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14, 17-20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Text and register are continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Copy trimmed with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Real presence --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Catholic Church --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38261:1"/>
            <p>AN EPISTLE OF A CATHOLIQUE To his Friend A PROTESTANT Touching the Doctrine of Reall Preſence.</p>
            <p>OR, The Anſwer to a Queſtion propounded in theſe Tearms.</p>
            <p>What ſhould move you, contrary to the plain Teſtimony of your Senſes, to believe, that after Conſecration the Bread and Wine in the Sacrament is become REALLY Chriſts very Body and Blood.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 22.29.</hi>
               </bibl> Ye doe erre, not KNOWING the Scriptures, nor the POWER of God.</q>
            <q>It is a manifeſt ſigne of an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NBELIEVING Heart, in the Works of God to ask HOW This or That can be. <bibl>
                  <hi>St. Baſil. lib. 5. contr. Eunom.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:38261:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38261:2"/>
            <head>An Epiſtle of a Catholique to his Friend a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant touching the Doctrine of <hi>Real Preſence.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu having deſired me to give you ſome probable Reaſons, which did, or do perſwade me to believe, that after the words of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, the Bread, contrary to the Senſes of Seeing, and Feeling, and Taſting, is Chriſts very Body, and the Wine his Blood; in anſwer to your demand, I ſhall, according to my weak Capacity, tell you truly by what Reaſons I am chiefly ſo perſwaded.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Holy Scriptures unanimouſly in expreſſe tearms ſay, That it is his Body, and that it is his Blood: the places in the Evangeliſts are ſo manifeſt and well known, that it may ſeem needleſs to name them; however for the importance of the matter I quote them to you. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26, 28. <hi>Mark</hi> 14.22, 24. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.19, 20.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Ancient Fathers did never underſtand thoſe places other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then in their literal and proper ſenſe; as appeareth by their Works left in writing, which are too numerous here to inſert: and is acknowledged by many of the moſt eminent Proteſtants themſelves, as namely, <hi>Philip Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon,</hi> the Centuriſts, <hi>Bucer, Peter Martyr, Calvin,</hi> and others; as you may ſee in the Book called <hi>The Progeny of Catholiques and Proteſtants. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>pag.</hi> 35, 36, 37. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it was the unanimous Doctrine of the Councels: not one of them ever determining the contrary, though at ſome times moved ſo to have done by ſome few private perſons, that Heretically oppoſed the Doctrine; and many of the ſaid Councels having expreſly determined for it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it was ever the conſtant Belief and Practice of the univerſall Church throughout the world: and whenſoever any did oppoſe it, they were preſently judged, condemned, and caſt out by the Church of that Age, as Heretiques, and in all after ages ſo likewiſe eſteemed, namely Heretiques, and their memory held abominable: ſtinking like to thoſe Carcaſes (<hi>Eſay</hi> 66.24.) which it is not improbable the Prophet in Spirit might principally mean, when he ſaid that <hi>the Carcaſes of the men that had tranſgreſſed,</hi> being caſt out, <hi>ſhall be an abhorring to all fleſh.</hi> For ſo indeed moſt commonly are the memories of all Heretiques; they are an abhorring, not onely to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church, but to all fleſh: for the latter Heretiques do, in one kinde or other, uſually condemn the former as much as Catholiques do.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, the Diviſions and Differences, which are among thoſe, whoſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in this matter be contrary to the Church, are ſo many and manifold,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38261:3"/>that it is not eaſie to reckon them; and do clearly convince, that there can be no certainty of Truth in any of their ſaid different opinions. <hi>Luther</hi> in his time obſerved Eight ſeveral Expoſitions of thoſe words, <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum, (This is my Body)</hi> all contrary one to another, and coming (as he ſaith) not from the Spirit of God, but <hi>from the mouth of Devils;</hi> and not long after him <hi>Claudius de Sainctes,</hi> a learned Biſhop of the Catholique Church, in his Book of the Euchariſt, reckoned no leſs then fourſcore diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Expoſitions of the ſaid words of Inſtitution, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>this is my Blood,</hi> &amp;c. all earneſtly maintained by learned Proteſtants with reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the contrary ſenſe. So that we ſee, once out of the way of true ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding of Scripture, and there's no end of erring. <hi>Luther</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolſtadius, Zuinglius,</hi> and <hi>Oecolampadius,</hi> (all three Sacramentarians, as he calls them) ſaith, <hi>Curſed be their Charity and Concord for ever and ever;</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, that he would have nothing to do with them in the matter of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. He ſaid moreover, that they expounded the words, <hi>This is my Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> as abſurdly, as if one ſhould expound that Text in the Book of Geneſis, <hi>In the beginning God made heaven and earth,</hi> thus, <hi>The Cuckow did eat up the Tittling,</hi> (or <hi>Hedge-Sparrow</hi>) <hi>bones and all:</hi> and as for that Paſſage of Saint <hi>John,</hi> Chap 1. v. 14. of his Goſpel, <hi>The word was made fleſh,</hi> their Expoſition, ſaith <hi>Luther,</hi> is as good as to ſay, <hi>A crooked ſtaff is made a Kite.</hi> Thus did <hi>Luther</hi> not without cauſe ſet out and deride the Sacramentarians expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Scripture, as you may ſee more at large noted <hi>pag.</hi> 22. of the Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Charks</hi> Preface called <hi>The Triall of Spirits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, if the words <hi>This is my Body</hi> be to be expounded thus, <hi>This is a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure,</hi> or, <hi>This is a ſign of my Body,</hi> then is there no hard myſtery, no <hi>hard ſaying</hi> at all in thoſe words; nor in thoſe other which our Saviour ſpake, <hi>John</hi> 6.53. <hi>Except ye eat the fleſh of the Son of man, and drink his blood, ye have no life in you:</hi> which were utterly contrary, not onely to the ſpeeches, language, and confeſſions of all Writers, and of all Records of Antiquity, which acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a great difficulty and hardneſs in this Myſtery, and a great irreconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able repugnancy to carnal ſenſe and Reaſon; that the Euchariſt (or Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) ſhould be verily and truly Chriſts Body and Blood; but contrary to the whole purport of our Lords Anſwer to the Capernaites, whoſe great ſtumbling queſtion was, how Chriſt could give them his fleſh to eat. This both They, and alſo ſome of his Diſciples, called <hi>an hard ſaying;</hi> they could not underſtand how it ſhould be done: nor yet by the Anſwer which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour gave them, did they, or indeed could they in reaſon, underſtand it as the Sacramentarians now do, to wit, that the Bread (in a Spiritual ſenſe) is onely a figure of his Body, and not his very Body indeed. For what <hi>hardneſs</hi> had there been then to conceive, and comprehend the full nature of the Myſtery? eſpecially how could his <hi>Saying</hi> have been thought ſo <hi>hard,</hi> that it ſhould move many of Chriſts own Diſciples to leave him, and to walk no longer
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38261:3"/>with him. And ſurely a ſad parting it was, ſeeing our Lord preſently upon it ſaid, as it were mournfully, to the Twelve, <hi>and will ye alſo go away?</hi> And yet notwithſtanding, though it were for their ſatisfaction, and to keep them from going away with the reſt, our Saviour (even he who is ſo great a lover of ſouls) thought fit to make them no other anſwer but this, <hi>Doth this offend you? what if you ſhall ſee the Son of man aſcend up where he was before, John</hi> 6.62. as much as if he had ſaid, though I do aſcend and leave you, yet of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity my fleſh muſt be eaten, and my blood be drunken, for otherwiſe life can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be had; if therefore this ſaying, <hi>You muſt eat the fleſh of the Son of man, and drink his blood,</hi> offend you now, and ſeem an <hi>hard ſaying</hi> to you now, while he is preſent with you, what will it do then, when you ſhall ſee him leave you, and aſcend up in his Body into heaven, <hi>where he was before?</hi> how will you then think it poſſible to eat his fleſh? This (I ſay) was the effect of our Lords anſwer to them, concerning their wondering how they ſhould be able to eat Chriſts fleſh, and their being ſcandalized at it as a thing altogether impoſſible, as you may ſee, <hi>John</hi> 6.53, 54. Whence ſurely it appeareth, that if either our Saviour had expounded himſelf to mean, or they had under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood it that he did mean, that his fleſh ſhould be eaten and his blood drunk <hi>in a ſign or figure</hi> onely, that ſpeech of his, <hi>what if you ſhall ſee the Son of man aſcend up where he was before,</hi> could have had no ſufficient reaſon. For doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the ſign (or figure) of his Body, whatſoever it were, might eaſily enough be eaten by them, after that his Body ſhould be aſcended. To take Bread, and to break it, in token that Chriſts Body was broken for us upon the Croſs, is no ſuch <hi>hard</hi> thing, but that it may be done as well in Chriſts abſence, as in his preſence, yea ſomething more properly in his abſence, then in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, at leaſt then in his viſible, natural and ordinary preſence: but now it is clear, our Saviour in that place mentions his Aſcenſion to his Diſciples, as a thing that ſhould make the myſtery of eating his fleſh to ſeem more difficult to them, and not leſs; therefore he meant they ſhould eat it, more then in a bare ſign, or figure onely: for that (I ſay) they might as eaſily do, when he were in heaven, as while he was on earth.</p>
            <p>Moreover our Lord knowing, that the Capernaites looked upon him as <hi>a meer man;</hi> and alſo that, while he ſpake of giving them his fleſh to eat, they underſtood him in a groſs and carnal manner, as that he ſhould give them his fleſh cut in pieces to eat, or the like; to extinguiſh and take away that groſs conceit out of their mindes, he telleth them, that <hi>Fleſh,</hi> to wit, according to their groſs manner of underſtanding, <hi>profitteth nothing.</hi> But now firſt, his Fleſh, was not meer humane fleſh, as they apprehended it, but it was the fleſh of the Son of God, yea of the <hi>true God,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.20. it was fleſh united to the Deity; and therefore in reſpect of other common fleſh, (whether of Beaſts or Men) Chriſts Body was to be accounted, rather a Spiritual and Divine Body, rather Spiritual and Divine Fleſh, then natural and common. It was the Lords Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38261:4"/>who came down from heaven, and is eternally, from everlaſting to everlaſting, alwayes in heaven; it was a Body full of grace and excellent vertue, and alſo a Body full of divine and incomprehenſible Myſtery. It was a Body Incarnate by the Holy Ghoſt without man, and born of a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin without forcing or violating the Womb; a Body that paſſed through a multitude, and was not diſcerned, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.30. compared with <hi>John</hi> 8.59. A Body that went out of the Sepulchre, not forcing away the ſtone, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.2, 5, 6. That came into the room, where the Diſciples were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together, <hi>the doors being ſhut,</hi> John 20.19. it came in, I ſay, <hi>and ſtood in the midſt of them,</hi> before they ever perceived it, juſt as if it had been a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; and inſomuch as the Diſciples, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.36, 37. took it verily to have been a ſpirit. And therefore of ſuch a Body as this, and of ſuch a Perſon as Chriſt was (God even the true God, bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſed for ever) to ſay, <hi>how can this man give us his fleſh to eat,</hi> or how can the Sacrament rightly conſecrated be his Body, is a fooliſh and an infidel queſtion. For he can do it well enough; he can give us his fleſh to eat, and his bloud to drink, though our ſenſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it not: and though (as he ſaith) we muſt eat his Body, yet his Body re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth alwayes whole; it is not to be cut or torn in pieces, as the Caper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naites imagined: for he doth not ſay, he would give us a piece of his fleſh, or a part of his fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh, but <hi>his fleſh</hi> entirely, that is to ſay, his whole Body, the entire Humanity which he received of the Bleſſed Virgin; this he would give to every one of us. He can do all things; to him nothing is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. He was with two of his Diſciples at <hi>Emmaus,</hi> talking with them, and converſing with them, and immediately vaniſhed out of their ſight, and was preſent with other Diſciples at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as may be gathered from <hi>Luke</hi> 24.29, 31. compared with <hi>John</hi> 20.19. And though he be alwayes at the right hand of God in Heaven, as appears <hi>Acts</hi> 3.22. yet is he alſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times (when he pleaſes) upon earth to convert ſinners, as for example <hi>Saul, Acts</hi> 9.17.27. and to comfort the faithful in their priſons, as <hi>Acts</hi> 23.11. He can do all things, I ſay; he can (as God) do whatſoever he pleaſeth in Heaven and Earth. What are we then (ſilly creatures) to queſtion, how he can give us his fleſh to eat, ſeeing he hath ſaid, that we muſt eat it, or periſh.</p>
            <p>But ſtill you object, and ſay, that this Doctrine, <hi>viz.</hi> that Bread ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Chriſts real Body in truth and ſubſtance, is ſo ſtrangly abſurd, that you cannot believe it. I anſwer, no more could the Jews, nor ſome of his Diſciples; of whom therefore (as taxing and noting their incredulity thereby) our Lord ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 6.64, 65. <hi>That no man can come unto him,</hi> and believe his words, <hi>except it were given him from above:</hi> and if there had been nothing, that is, no greater myſtery, in theſe words of Chriſt, <hi>This is my Body, &amp;c.</hi> but onely this, <hi>viz.</hi> a figure or ſign of my Body, what needed all that conteſt, ſo long, ſo difficult about the words, as was betwixt Chriſt and the Jews? Yea then have the univerſal Church, Councels, Fathers, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38261:4"/>and all been deceived; for never any of them all took the Sacrament to be onely a Figure of Chriſts Body.</p>
            <p>But you ſay you cannot believe it. Tell me; Is it not as eaſie for our hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Reaſon to conceive that the Bread, which our Lord ſaid was his Body, ſhould be ſo indeed, as it is to conceive, that the little Babe, ſucking at his Virgin-Mothers breaſt, was the Creatour of the whole Univerſe, both of the Heavens and Earth, of the Sea, and of all things therein contained? Is it not as eaſie for a Chriſtian to believe this Doctrine, as to believe, that the little Babe in the Manger, whom the three Sages adored, was the Almighty God? Faith may and muſt believe theſe things, though ſenſe and reaſon cannot. Therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.5. of <hi>captivating our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and every thought and imagination to the obedience of Chriſt;</hi> and <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.5. he ſaith, that the Goſpel is made known unto all Nations for <hi>the obedience of Faith,</hi> that is to ſay, that by faith, and by believing all that the Goſpel required of them, men might ſhew themſelves to be entirely obedient and ſubject unto God, in their underſtandings no leſs then in their affections and wills. And truly conſidering the way and order of God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighties dealings with the ſons of men, we ought not to think it ſtrange, that he ſhould, in this particular of eating, require a renuntiation of our ſenſes. We may do well to remember, that when time was, by following our ſenſes contrary unto Gods command, we loſt Paradiſe; and if now by obeying God contrary to our ſenſes, Paradiſe may be regained, we ſhall have no great cauſe to murmure. So that indeed this Impoſition of believing and eating contrary to our ſenſes, ſeems (as it were) a certain Penance, which God layes upon man for his firſt and great ſin; to the end, that as by fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing his ſenſes contrary to Gods expreſs word and command, <hi>Adam</hi> loſt Heaven and eternal happineſs, as much as in him lay; ſo by an obedient and ſubmiſſive Faith in Gods word and unto his command, renouncing the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of our own ſenſe and all ſuggeſtions of fleſh and blood, the ſons of <hi>Adam</hi> might, through Grace, recover Heaven and eternal happineſs.</p>
            <p>Senſe and natural Reaſon tells <hi>Naaman,</hi> that the Rivers of <hi>Damaſcus</hi> were as likely to cure him of his Leproſie, as <hi>Jordan</hi> in <hi>Judea,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5.12. but he found it otherwiſe. So it was contrary to ſenſe, and contrary to all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural reaſon, that the walls of <hi>Jericho</hi> ſhould fall down at <hi>Iſraels</hi> blowing with Rams-horns; yet we know they did ſo, <hi>Joſhua</hi> 6.20. Contrary to ſenſe <hi>Moſes</hi> divided the Sea by the ſtroak of a rod, <hi>Exodus</hi> 14.16, 21. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to ſenſe <hi>Jordan</hi> divided it ſelf, as ſoon as it was but touched by the feet of the Prieſts, <hi>Joſhua</hi> 3.15, 16. And contrary to ſenſe Iron did ſwimme, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6.6. It was contrary to ſenſe, that a little meal and oyl (no more then would make one cake) ſhould feed the Widow, the Prophet, and her Son many dayes, or a long time together, and not waſte, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.12, 16. It was contrary to ſenſe, that five loaves and two fiſhes ſhould ſatisfie the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38261:5"/>hunger of five thouſand perſons; and that there ſhould remain twelve baskets full of broken meat, after all had eaten, <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.20. <hi>Mark</hi> 6.43. <hi>John</hi> 6.13. Conſidering the deadneſs of <hi>Sarahs</hi> womb, as the Scripture ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.19. and alſo of <hi>Abrahams</hi> own body, it was contrary to ſenſe and re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſon, that <hi>Sarah</hi> ſhould have a childe; yet <hi>Abraham</hi> believing what God had ſaid to him, his Faith found the effect of the promiſe, and it was counted to him for righteouſnes For by believing, ſaith the Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.20. he gave glory to God, and was counted <hi>the friend of God,</hi> James 2.23. So is it in this matter and myſtery of the Euchariſt; they that believe what our Saviour hath ſaid, and accordingly truſt thereupon, give glory to God by this their believing, yea are made thereby and eſteemed the friends of God, to wit, ſo far as they do not fruſtrate, or make void the merit of their faith by the demerit and wickedneſs of their lives. Many other places and examples might be alledged, that demonſtrate Gods people alwayes to have walked with God by faith, and not by ſenſe: and why not then in this Myſtery as well as in others? why ſhould this Doctrine ſeem ſo ſtrange to men of underſtanding and knowledge in the wayes of God, conſidering the greatneſs of the Almighty, and how he vails his will and myſteries of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes unto us? Conſidering how terrible in the Old Teſtament he was to ſuch as would pry into his wayes and ſecrets further then was permitted them; how fearful the wiſer ſort of Jews were ſo to do; and laſtly how anſwerable the practice of the univerſal Church of Chriſt hath been in this thing, and that for above ſixteen hundred years, namely to walk by faith ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then by ſenſe in this buſineſs, and to reſt more upon the Word, and Power, and Truth of God, then upon our own reaſon or underſtanding. Conſider I pray what the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Iſa</hi> 7.9. <hi>If ye will not believe, ſurely you ſhall not be eſtabliſhed.</hi> By reaſon of unbelief was that Lord, on whoſe hand the King leaned, trodden to death in the gate of <hi>Samaria,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 7.20. A believing heart is the root of all ſpiritual excellency and acceptable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with God; and it is the character which he gives them. <hi>I take to witneſs,</hi> ſaith God, 2 Eſdras 1.37. <hi>the grace of the people to come,</hi> (meaning the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, ſuch as ſhould believe in the <hi>Meſſias</hi> that was to come) <hi>whoſe little ones,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>rejoyce in gladneſs, and though they have not ſeen me with bodily eyes, yet in ſpirit they believe the things that I ſay.</hi> Hitherto alſo comes that ſaying of our Lord to St. <hi>Thomas, Becauſe thou haſt ſeen me, Thomas, thou believeſt;</hi> but <hi>bleſſed are they that have not ſeen, and yet have believed,</hi> John 20.29. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us not diſpute, but rather pray to the Almighty to captivate our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings to the obedience of Faith, that we may here, in reverence to his word, be willing to believe what we do not ſee, that ſo hereafter, in the bliſsful viſion of his glory, we may be admitted to ſee more then we do now believe.</p>
            <p>And beſides all this, the Prophetical Types and Shadows of the Sacrifices
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38261:5"/>in the Law, as alſo the Prophetical ſayings, or predictions of the Prophets, concerning ſomewhat of greater worth and far exceeding the dignity of Moſaical Sacrifices, that ſhould be ſacrificed and eaten under the Goſpel, are a further and undeniable argument, that the Euchariſt is not a figure onely of Chriſts Body, but his very real and true Body. 'Tis granted by all, at leaſt by the moſt learned and ingenuous amongſt Proteſtants, to wit, by all ſuch as pretend any ſhew of reſpect to Antiquity, that thoſe Propheſies of the old Teſtament, do point at the Euchariſt, or Sacrament of Chriſts Body in the new. Now if the Sacramentarian opinion be true, to wit, that the Bread of the Euchariſt remains ſtill, even after Conſecration, in truth and ſubſtance but a morſel of Bread, and nothing elſe, and the Wine, after Conſecration, nothing but meer Wine, how is the Sacrament of the Euchariſt a more noble and excellent thing, then were the Sacraments and Sacrifices of the Jews? for they alſo were no leſs ſigns and figures of Chriſts Body, then the Bread of the Euchariſt is. Yea who ſees not, that the Jewiſh Sacrifices upon this ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Euchariſtical Bread is indeed nothing but Bread, and the Euchariſtical Wine nothing but Wine; I ſay, who ſeeth not upon this ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, that the Jewiſh Sacrifices far exceeded the Chriſtians in the worth and dignity of the things ſacrificed? for example, the Paſchal Lamb, was it not a more excellent Sacrifice in its own nature, then a piece of bare Bread? But now <hi>Malachy</hi> propheſieth that under the new Law ſhould that more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Sacrifice be. He propheſieth that God would reject and caſt away the Prieſthood and Sacrifices of the Jews, and inſtead of them, would have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more pure and more excellent Sacrifice: and that not offered in Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem onely, or in any one place, or city of the world, but all the world over, from the riſing of the Sun to the going down thereof, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.11. Neither can this be any other but the Body of our Lord offered upon the Altar; which upon the rejection of <hi>Moſes</hi> daily Sacrifice, was to come in place and to be accepted of God, according to that of the Pſalmiſt, ſpeaking in the perſon of Chriſt, <hi>Burnt-offering and ſacrifice for ſin thou wouldeſt not have, but a Body thou haſt fitted me, Pſal.</hi> 40.6. according to the Tranſlation of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuagint; which St. <hi>Paul</hi> likewiſe followeth, leaving the Hebrew, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.5. Doubtleſs by vertue of the word of God in the Prieſts mouth, this Body is <hi>fitted</hi> both for a Sacrament, and alſo a Sacrifice, after the order of <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech:</hi> who being the firſt-born of a great and honorable family in <hi>Salem,</hi> was according to the cuſtom of that age, both Prince and Prieſt there, as <hi>Jethro</hi> was in <hi>Midian, Exod.</hi> 18.1. And ſo likewiſe our Lord, being <hi>the firſt-born among many Brethren, Rom.</hi> 8.29. and <hi>the firſt-born of every creature,</hi> as he is called, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.15. is therefore by God the Father, and that by an oath, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained a Prieſt for ever after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech:</hi> whoſe ſacrifice, as the learned affirm, was Bread and Wine firſt offered in ſacrifice to God, and afterwards eaten by ſuch as participated of the ſacrifices, as appears, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. where it is not improbably thought, that with part of the Bread and Wine
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38261:6"/>which <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> brought forth, as a <hi>Prieſt of the moſt high God,</hi> he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed <hi>Abraham</hi> returning from the ſlaughter of the four Kings. So that as the Aaronical, or Moſaical ſacrifices of Beaſts were types and figures of our Lords Bloudy ſacrifice of himſelf upon the Croſs for the ſins of the world; ſo in like manner was <hi>Melchiſedechs</hi> ſacrifice in Bread and Wine a figure of our Lords unbloudy ſacrificing of himſelf upon the Altar for the Church. Which unbloudy Sacrifice our Lord did inſtitute and ordain at his laſt Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, when he ſaid to his Apoſtles, <hi>Do this, Luke</hi> 22.19. and which Action of our Saviour, was by the Apoſtles, who were eye-witneſſes thereof, celebrated in like manner throughout the world, to wit, in all parts and in all places where they preached the Goſpel; and hath been ever ſince continued in the univerſal Church to this day.</p>
            <p>The word which our Tranſlation reads <hi>miniſtring, Acts</hi> 13.2. as the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed affirm, ſignifies in the Greek properly <hi>ſacrificing,</hi> and ſo 'tis tranſlated by <hi>Eraſmus; As they were ſacrificing to the Lord, and faſting, the Holy Ghoſt ſaid, Separate unto me Saul and Barnabas.</hi> The Sacrifice of the Croſs was a bloudy and general Sacrifice for the ſins of the whole world: but this of the Altar is unbloudy, and more particular for the Church, but moſt eſpecially for thoſe members of the Church for whom in particular it is offered. The Jews had their Meat-offerings, and Drink-offerings, and Bloudy Sacrifices; to which Chriſt anſwereth. Upon the Croſs he was that Bloudy Sacrifice, which fulfilleth that which was typified by thoſe bloudy Sacrifices of the Beaſts that were killed: upon the Altar he is the unbloudy Sacrifice, and fulfilleth the Types of thoſe Sacrifices, wherein there was no ſhedding of bloud; ſuch as were the Meat-offerings, and Drink-offerings, and the like. The Paſchal Lamb was in a diverſe reſpect both a bloudy Sacrifice, and alſo an unbloudy; and therefore our Saviour anſwers the Type of it in both reſpects. As it was a Lamb taken out of the flock and killed, and the bloud ſprinkled upon the door-poſts; ſo it was a bloudy Sacrifice; and ſo our Saviour fulfils the Type of it by the offering of himſelf up to death upon the Croſs: but as it was to be roſted afterward with fire, and the fleſh eaten within the houſe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.7, 8. it is unbloudy, and a Type of the Sacrifice of the Altar, which is eaten within the Houſe, that is to ſay, within the Church, by the Members of the Church onely; Jews and Gentiles, with all Excommunicated perſons, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, Schiſmatiques, and the like, being excluded and not permitted to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take thereof. Alſo to the great comfort of all Catholique Chriſtians, the general Sacrifice of the Croſs is applied particularly, in the Sacrifice of the Altar, to the Church and to the true members thereof, for whom in ſpecial it is offered. This, I ſay, is a great and unſpeakable comfort and benefit; here doth our Lord meet with us. God commanding the Jews to offer the Sacrifices of Beaſts at the door of the Tabernacle, ſaid, that he would <hi>there meet with them, Exod.</hi> 29.43. Certainly this was a great comfort to the Jew; but<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hath not the Chriſtian as great? yes certainly, and far greater. If he come
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38261:6"/>as he ought, well prepared to the Altar of God, if his hands be cleanſed in innocency, and his heart purified from the conſcience of ſin through faith and true repentance, he comes (as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Heb</hi> 4.16.) and that with <hi>boldneſs,</hi> or great confidence, <hi>unto the throne of grace, and findeth help in time of need.</hi> There doth our Lord vouchſafe to meet with us (Cathol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>que Chriſtians) not by vertue of the bloud of Bulls and of Beaſts, in which the Father ſaid, <hi>he had no pleaſure;</hi> but by vertue of his own bloud, in which Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice the Father teſtifieth that <hi>he was well pleaſed. Burnt offerings and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>thou hadſt no pleaſure in;</hi> but then ſaith the Son, <hi>Lo I come, to do thy will, O God,</hi> as it followeth in the Pſalm laſt cited.</p>
            <p>O thou Chriſtian, come thou then to this Altar in faith, come in innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, come in charity, come prepared, come reverently: ſerve the Lord with trembling, and rejoyce with fear; for our God is a conſuming fire. <hi>We have an Altar,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.10. <hi>of which they have no right to eat, which ſerve the Tabernacle,</hi> meaning the Jew; among whom though the Prieſts might eat of ſome offerings, yet they might not eat of the <hi>Sin-offering;</hi> that was to be burnt <hi>without the gate, Lev.</hi> 4.12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.30. But the Chriſtian Law offereth more Grace. Our Lord, who was made an <hi>offering for ſin, Eſay</hi> 53. ſaith to all, both Prieſts and People, that <hi>except they eat the fleſh of the Son of man, and drink his bloud,</hi> they cannot have life: yet he was an offering for ſin, and alſo ſuffered without the gate of Jeruſalem, as the Sin-offering was commanded to be burnt without the gate, of which the Prieſts of <hi>Moſes</hi> might not eat: but the Chriſtian may eat of the Sin-offering of Chriſts Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; yea he muſt eat of it, if he will have life and benefit by it. Therefore it is, that the Apoſtle ſaith of Chriſtians, that they have ſuch an Altar, (<hi>viz.</hi> an Altar of a ſin-offering) as the Jewiſh ſervitours of the Tabernacle were not allowed to partake of. And by this we may ſee, that all myſteries whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever covered in the Law under Types and Shadows, (whether Burnt-offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Meat-offerings, Free-will-offerings, Heave-offerings, yea the very Sin-offering it ſelf, with the Altars both within the Vaile and without) have all relation to Chriſts Sufferings, Paſſion, and Death, commemorated at the Chriſtian Altar. And not onely theſe, but the Mercy-ſeat alſo, the Ark, which even under the Law to pry into was preſent death, do all contain ſome myſtery of Chriſt, and which alwayes required them not to be look't into by the eye of ſenſe, but the eye of faith. There the Cherubims ſtand over the Mercy-ſeat, their faces looking down upon it, but their wings ſpread out, <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.18, 19, 20. ſignifying that under a Type, which the Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter</hi> plainly expreſſeth, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12. namely, that the very Angels themſelves deſire <hi>to look into,</hi> and to be made acquainted with the great myſteries of God revealed in Chriſt: the myſteries, I ſay, which were hid in God from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and by his Apoſtles and Prophets made known unto his Church, and by the Church unto the Angels themſelves, even <hi>to the higheſt Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and Powers in heavenly places, Epheſ.</hi> 3.9, 10. For they are all of them by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38261:7"/>office <hi>miniſtring Spirits, ſent out to miniſter for them who ſhall be heirs of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> that is, for the ſervice and Protection of the Church, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Church,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Glory ſhall be given to God throughout all ages:</hi> whence it appears, that there is not one age, or ever ſhall be, wherein the Church of God is not in being: in this Church are the myſteries of Chriſtianity celebrated, but more eſpecially, as the Fathers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly teach, <hi>in the adorable Sacrifice of the Altar:</hi> great myſteries indeed, and for the right underſtanding of which, faith and not ſenſe, hath its exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe: here we muſt believe, not reaſon and diſpute from principles of Senſe, Nature, and Philoſophy: That is a thing, which the Apoſtle forbids and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warns us of, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.8. We muſt believe, I ſay, that the Bread duly conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted is no longer Bread, but that very Body of Chriſt, which God the Father Almighty <hi>hath fitted,</hi> and ordained to be a daily Sacrifice, offered up to God after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> according as it is written of Chriſt, <hi>Thou art a Prieſt for ever after the order of Melchiſedech, Pſal.</hi> 110.4. And when this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice totally and unverſally ceaſeth, then the world ſhall end, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.27. compared with <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.15. But before this can be, ſaith our Lord, <hi>the Goſpel muſt be preached for a Teſtimony in all Nations, and then ſhall the end come.</hi> Therefore, ſaith Chriſt, when you ſee the Propheſie of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> come to paſs, then <hi>let him that readeth, underſtand,</hi> for the end is near. Hitherto comes that ſaying of the Jewiſh Rabbins, noted by <hi>Ainſworth</hi> on <hi>Leviticus,</hi> Chap. 5. v. 15. <hi>Our wiſe men have ſaid,</hi> ſay the Rabbins, that <hi>for the ſervice of the Sacrifice the world doth continue:</hi> whence it may be collected, that if the daily Sacrifice of Chriſts Body, (of which the Jewiſh Sacrifices were but Types and Shadows) if that comes once to be totally and univerſally abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, the world will quickly be at an end. Moreover, the ſame Rabbins affirm, that the myſteries contained in their Sacrifices, are ſo great, that the meaning of them cannot be fully attained in this world; and therefore, ſaith Mr. <hi>Ainſworth,</hi> they adviſe people not to be over curious to pry into them preſumptuouſly, leſt God break out upon them, as he threatneth to do, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.12, 24. <hi>Thou ſhalt,</hi> ſaith God to <hi>Moſes, ſet bounds, that the people go not up into the mount:</hi> and it was of ſuch conſequence, that the people might not preſume to prie, that God ſaid the ſecond and third time to <hi>Moſes Go down, and charge the people, that they break not thorow to gaze, and I break out upon them, and many periſh,</hi> ver. 21. The Bethſhemites but onely for looking into the Ark, or Cheſt wherein the Book of the Law was kept, God ſmote of the people no leſs then fifty thouſand and ſeventy men, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.19. Surely a terrible warning this muſt be to us, if we duly conſider it.</p>
            <p>By all which we may ſee, (as the ſame <hi>Aynſworth</hi> alſo notes) that inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive curioſity to have humane Reaſon and Senſe fully ſatisfied touching the myſteries of Religion, is a thing forbidden by God. Men muſt walk by faith in the things of God, and not by ſight, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. which conſidered, I leave it to you, and to all rational and indifferent men whatſoever, whether it be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38261:7"/>not ſafer, in this great myſtery of Chriſts Body on the Altar, whether it be not ſafer (I ſay) with the whole Chriſtian world of all ages, to Believe and Adore though contrary to ſenſe, rather then to pry and examine by ſenſe, or the dictates of carnal reaſon. For in Believing and Adoring I follow the pure word of God both of the Old and New Teſtament; I follow the Doctrine of the Ancient Fathers, the Decrees of Councels, and conſtant practice of the univerſal Church, and that from the one end of heaven to the other. Is it not ſafer (think you) to follow all theſe ſure and infallible Guids, rather then (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all theſe) to follow the conjectures of my own brain, or at beſt of ſome other particular Sect-maſter, or Sect-maſters? one of theſe three of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity I muſt follow: either the Catholique Church with the Ancient Fathers and lawful Paſtours of it; or elſe ſome particular Sect-maſter, or Sect-maſters, divided from the Church, and teaching contrary to the Churches ſenſe; or laſtly my own brain, my own private reaſon, ſpirit, or what elſe you will call it: for a fourth I cannot finde. And as ſuch a Sect-maſter is followed in this world, ſo let his followers make their account, that they ſhall ſtand with him before the judgement-ſeat of Chriſt; they ſhall not be ſeparated for ever: whom they loved to follow here in this world, contrary to duty, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the ordinance of Chriſt, (who commands us to hear his Church, and not particular Sect-maſters, either departed or cut off from the Church) they ſhall be made to follow and keep company with, againſt their wills, in the next life, in eternal flames and miſeries. I wiſh all would conſider this, who ſo eaſily put themſelves under the tuition of every private and preſumptuous Sect-maſter, that they would conſider it, I ſay, and return in time to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and communion of the Catholique Church, which onely hath lawful Authority to teach them, and alſo a faithful promiſe from Chriſt to teach them Truth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.20. <hi>John</hi> 14.16, 17.</p>
            <p>And beſide all this, is it not even miraculous to conſider, that the univerſal Church, all Ancient Fathers, both in and out of Councels, and that in all ages ſince Chriſt, ſhould believe and hold a thing ſo repugnant and abſurd to ſenſe and all humane reaſon, as Sectaries make the Faith of Catholicks in this point ſeem to be? and that the generation of Catholiques ſhould do and believe this from age to age to almoſt ſeventeen hundred years; and this without any ſelf or by-ends, of profit, pleaſure, honour, or other intereſt whatſoever, but purely for conſcience ſake, and out of obedience to Gods word, and to the Catholique Doctrine of Chriſtianity? This certainly may ſeem no leſs then a miracle in our eyes; we muſt confeſs the finger of God, and his ſpecial Providence to be in it, unleſs we be very partial: eſpecially if on the other ſide we do but conſider, how every other Sect that hath riſen, and upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of reforming abuſes and errors, hath ever perſecuted the Mother-Church, really for her not complying with them in their greater Errours; (as for example, the Arians in that of the Trinity, the Calviniſts in that of the Euchariſt, &amp;c. endeavouring ſtill to make the Church forſake her firſt Faith,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38261:8"/>and comply with them in their following of ſenſe and humane reaſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary unto Faith) I ſay, if we do but conſider, how ſhort-liv'd and how little or nothing prevailing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> both theſe and all other Sects have been; how they have been able to do nothing, but onely to procure diſturbance and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to good Chriſtians in ſome particular parts of the Church, we muſt needs more clearly ſee and acknowledge the hand of God in it; and that as it was their intent indeed, and endeavour to diſturb and deſtroy, ſo Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and purpoſe was to purifie his Church thereby, and to purge it of Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites and Time-ſervers, and ſuch like droſs. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> expreſſeth the evil practices of theſe men by the ſimilitude of barking Dogs; <hi>They bark</hi> (ſaith he in his Book <hi>de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tilit. cred. cap.</hi> 17. ſpeaking of Heretiques and Sectaries) <hi>They bark perpetually againſt the Apoſtolique Chair, but all in vain.</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y effect nothing by their barking. Yea he confeſſeth that even himſelf was a Barker too, all the time that he was a Manichean, that is, he was one that exerciſed the patience of true Chriſtians by detraction and other injurious treating of them. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19. <hi>There muſt be Hereſies among you, that they which are approved may be made manifeſt:</hi> and for that reaſon God permitteth ſome Hereſies and Sects, as it were, to reign and carry all before them for a time. By falſe Teachers, ſaith <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3, 4. God <hi>proveth you, whether ye will cleave unto the Lord your God with all your hearts and with all your ſouls.</hi> Nevertheleſs they alſo in time, declining the infallible rule of Faith, which is the Authority and Tradition of the Catholique Church, and refuſing to be obedient, and to captivate their underſtanding to the high myſteries of Faith, but following humane reaſon and their own private ſenſe, have vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and come to nothing. All their wit, and worldly glory, and power, and intereſt, and learning, could not preſerve them from the contempt and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of ſome contrary Sect.</p>
            <p>Witneſs the late Proteſtant Church of <hi>England.</hi> How was it it eſtabliſhed and ſecured, as to all humane judgement, from all danger, and from all fear of being ſo ſuddenly rooted up! How was the Government thereof ſettled by Biſhops, confirmed by Law, and countenanced by the State! Their form of Ordination, Articles, Sacraments, Liturgy, and their whole order of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, ſo regulated, and ſo ratified both by the Prince and State, that nothing could ſeem to be deſired more. Yet becauſe it was all of private judgement, all differing or contrary to the Tradition of the Catholique Church, and done either out of hatred, or contempt, or contradiction to the Apoſtolique Sea, whoſe Authority is the root and fountain of all true Chriſtian Eccleſiaſtical Unity, how ſuddenly is her day come! what a ſtrange, unexpected, unfeared judgement hath taken her away in the height of her worldly glory! For non-compliance ſhe perſecuted the children of her Mother-Church even to bloud, impriſoning multitudes of them unto death; but as for her Prieſts, hanging, and drawing, and quartering them, as Traitors and the moſt infamous of all ſorts of Malefactors whatſoever, and ſetting their fleſh upon poles, to be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38261:8"/>meat for the fowls of the ayr, and permitting none to bury them; and taking Two of Three parts of the Lands and goods of the Common people, that profeſſed themſelves Catholiques. But O ye, ſtand now amazed, and behold how ſhe is judged. She that was thus bottomed, ſtrengthned, and eſtabliſhed in her way of Religion and Church-government, ſhe that ſate as Queen, and ſaid in her heart, I ſhall ſee no widdow-hood, what is become of her? where is ſhe to be found in the whole earth? in leſs ſpace then one hundred of years, ſhe is both riſen and fallen, and come to nothing: and though her ſin in the puniſhment thereof be even written upon her forehead, yet ſhe repents not, but like the ſtrange woman in the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> ſhe <hi>wipes her mouth and ſaith, I have not ſinned, I have done no ill,</hi> I am not either Heretique or Sciſmatique. Our original Ordination was good; our compliance with Princes for our ſafety is warranted by the examples of ſome other Nations; though we have diſſented from our Mother-Church and from all the world beſide, in doctrine, in ordination of Prieſthood, in a Leiturgy and worſhipping of God, in the Sacraments and Church-government; yet all this is nothing, ſo long as (our ſelves being judges) we are one in Fundamentals, we are neither Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiques, nor Heretiques, how much ſoever we be outwardly caſt down. Thus they ſeem to plead. But O miſerable Apology! how unable is it to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie, or palliate Schiſme, eſpecially the Schiſme of them, who for ſo many years together have laboured the extirpation of that Church, which firſt brought them off from Paganiſme to Chriſtianity! Conſider this I pray, ye that are now upon the ſtage, that ye act not againſt Gods Church. Deſtroy it you cannot; perſecute it, trouble and afflict it you may for a time, ſo long as it pleaſes God to permit you; but you ſhall ſooner deſtroy your ſelves, then it. Remember what befel <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> who thought by oppreſſion to keep Iſrael low and weak; but his wiſdom proved folly. What became of <hi>Jerobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams</hi> wiſdom, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12. though he was made a King of the ten Tribes, yet he ought not to have altered Gods worſhip? 'Tis true, in doing ſo, his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy aimed onely at his own ſafety, but yet that proved his ruine.</p>
            <p>And for you my friends, (the Catholiques of this Nation) who have ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly in your Baptiſme promiſed and profeſſed to believe the Articles of Chriſtian Religion, and the Catholique Church; as alſo to forſake all that appertains <hi>to the luſt of the fleſh, to the luſt of the eyes, and pride of life, which are not of the Father, but of the Devil,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.16. in this Covenant be ye faithful to the death. The time we have to labour for Eternity is ſhort; but a ſhort moment: even as a drop of a bucket to the whole ocean ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and one gravel ſtone in compariſon of the ſands upon the ſea ſhore, ſo are a thouſand, yea a thouſand thouſands of years, to the dayes of Eternity. Therefore, <hi>O my ſoul.</hi> ſaith <hi>Eſdras,</hi> 2 <hi>Eſdras</hi> 8.4, 5. <hi>ſwallow down underſtanding, and devour wiſdom; for thou haſt no longer time, then onely to live,</hi> wherein thou muſt gain eternity. Wherefore, as the Preacher ſaith, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.10. <hi>whatſoever thy hand hath found to do</hi> (to wit, of good) <hi>do it with all thy might; for there is no labouring in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38261:9"/>grave.</hi> Let us now reſolutely and courageouſly reſign up our ſelves to all manner of afflictions for heavens ſake; and by ſo doing lay hold of eternal life: let us not let ſlip any opportunity; for in that way we ſhall beſt gather to our ſelves treaſures of glory: we may think our ſelves happy, as many of us, as in this kind and for this cauſe, ſuffer perſecution. Diverſe Catholique Countreys want this high favour from God, which we in <hi>England</hi> have. Such in other Countreys, as fix their eyes upon eternity, force themſelves to long and ſharp Penances, in Faſtings, Watchings, hard Labour, auſtere Diſcipline, with other mortifications of the fleſh: but inſtead of theſe, we in <hi>England</hi> have countrey-men and neighbours, perſecuting us to the loſs of goods, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and life, ſometimes. O, let us be content, and account, that this time is our Fair and Market; our Mart-time to get both precious, glorious, and durable riches to eternity. And as for thoſe, who are our Perſecutours, let us mourn and pray for them. Our Lord ſaid to the daughters of Jeruſalem, <hi>Weep not for me, but weep for your ſelves, and for your children.</hi> So I would to God, theſe would pitty themſelves, more then they pitty thoſe whom they perſecute; which yet ſometimes they ſeem to do. Let us pray earneſtly for them, and fear, that it is for ſome great foregoing ſins, ſtill aggravated and continued by our own iniquities, that hath ſo incenſed and moved the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful God to permit our neighbours to be our perſecuters, and that God uſes them as his Battle-ax, as the Rod of his wrath, and the Staff of his indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to puniſh Hypocrites, but to purge and purifie thoſe whom he loves. O 'tis a woful condition, that ſuch our perſecuters are in; let us pray heartily for them for their Converſion and amendment, before the Altar of our God; that it would pleaſe the merciful God of all fleſh, and Father of Spirits, to illuminate thoſe that live out of the Church, ſeriouſly to apprehend the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of their eſtate, and the great importance of eternal Salvation; and that it would pleaſe the Almighty to incline the hearts of our Magiſtrates, both rightly to underſtand our Religion, and impartially to conſider our Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: and however they oppreſs and perſecute us, yet, O Lord, make us ever with exact fidelity to perform our duties to them. And alſo let us pray, that God would be pleaſed to aſſwage his anger towards our Nation; to forgive the ſins of our forefathers and ours, and to turn away his wrath from us their poſtetity; to deliver the ignorant from being any longer ſeduced by falſe Teachers, and the learned from being miſlead by their worldly intereſts and paſſions; and the whole Nation from the Spirit of Contradiction, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſs and Diſcord; that inſtead of ſo many Sects, Diviſions and changes of Religion, they may all again be reſtored to that <hi>One True Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and to that unity of Minde, and ſteadineſs of Faith, and tranquillity of Conſcience, which is no where elſe to be ſought, no where elſe to be found, but in the Communion of Gods Church, nor by any other means to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, but by the conduct of his Grace.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb facs="tcp:38261:9"/>
            <head>An Appendix to the foregoing Diſcourſe, in Anſwer to an Objection, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHereas you object, that <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and ſome other of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, do call the Symbols of Bread and Wine after Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration, <hi>Figures onely;</hi> I wonder that you being a knowing man in theſe matters, ſhould thus ſpeak. That they call them <hi>Figures</hi> ſometimes its confeſt; and ſo do divers Catholick Writers of preſent times, as you may ſee in <hi>Bellarmin.</hi> (<hi>Libr.</hi> 1. <hi>de Sacram. Euchariſt. cap.</hi> 5) but that they called, or eſteemed, them <hi>Figures onely</hi> and no more, or Figures <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Subſtance,</hi> as Proteſtants do, is denied. The Holy Scripture calls the Son (<hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3.) <hi>the expreſs Image,</hi> or Figure, of <hi>his Fathers</hi> Subſtance, or <hi>Perſon:</hi> Is he not therefore of the ſame Subſtance, and Divine Nature with the Father? The Quakers indeed underſtand and eſteem him <hi>onely a Figure,</hi> becauſe of this Text: but the Church and all true Chriſtians believe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, namely, that though he be <hi>the Figure</hi> of God, yet he is alſo in the verity of his own Perſon true and eternal God; and <hi>that in him dwelleth all the fulneſs of the Godhead bodily,</hi> Col. 2.9. And therefore for you to ſay, that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers eſteemed the Sacrament duly conſecrated to be a <hi>Figure onely</hi> of Chriſts Body, is a great miſtake and undervaluing of the Fathers Judgements; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing them to be ſo ſtupid, that they ſhould both Adore, and alſo Offer up to God, as a Sacrifice of ſuch Divine Vertue and Merit, and of ſo Supream and Superlative Excellency above all other Sacrifices whatſoever that had been offered before it, that which was in it ſelf but a piece of Bread, a thing ſo much inferiour even to the meaneſt of the Jewiſh Sacrifices. I ſay, that the Fathers ſhould thus Magnifie and Adore that which they believed to be nothing elſe but a piece of bread, is the greateſt abſurdity that can be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon men. But you wil not believe (perhaps) that the Fathers <hi>Adored</hi> the Sacrament. To convince you of this, I ſhall alledge ſome few examples (of many) out of their Works; by which it will undeniably appear, what both their judgement and practice was concerning this matter.</p>
            <p>Firſt, St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> (<hi>Epiſt.</hi> 118.) ſaith, <hi>It is he the Apoſtle ſaith ſhall be</hi> dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>who doth not with</hi> SINGULAR VENERATION, or Adoration, <hi>make a difference betwixt this meat and all other meats.</hi> And again (upon the 98. Pſalm) <hi>No man,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>eateth this Sacrament, but firſt he Adoreth it.</hi> Secondly, St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> (<hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. <hi>de Spir. Sanct.</hi>) <hi>We</hi> ADORE (ſaith he) <hi>the fleſh of Chriſt in the Myſteries.</hi> Thirdly, St. <hi>Chryſoſtome Homil.</hi> 24. <hi>in</hi> 1. <hi>ad Cor. We</hi> ADORE <hi>him on the Altar, as the Wiſemen did in the Manger,</hi> Matth. 2.11. Fourthly, St. <hi>Gregory Nazianzen (in Epitaph. Gorgon.)</hi> profeſſeth of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout
<pb facs="tcp:38261:10"/>and Faithful Siſter <hi>Gorgonia,</hi> that being in a diſtreſs ſhe ran to the Church, and caſting her ſelf down before the Altar, <hi>invocated,</hi> or called upon <hi>Chriſt who is adored,</hi> or worſhipped, <hi>thereon.</hi> Fifthly, <hi>Theodoret.</hi> (<hi>dial.</hi> 2. entituled <hi>Inconfuſus</hi>) <hi>The Myſtical Symbols</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are</hi> ADORED, <hi>as being in truth the things they are believed to be,</hi> to wit, the Body and Blood of Chriſt. Laſtly, St. <hi>Dennis Areopagita,</hi> Scholar of the Apoſtles themſelves, (<hi>Eccleſiaſt. Hierarch. cap.</hi> 3. <hi>part.</hi> 3.) makes a ſolemn Prayer expreſly to the Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament upon the Altar; and generally all the Ancient Leiturgies of the Church do ſhew, that at the time of Elevation, and whenſoever the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated Symbols were openly preſented, eſpecially before Receiving, the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of the Church was with one voice to make their prayers unto it, in theſe and the like words; <hi>Lamb of God, that takeſt away the ſins of the world, have mercy upon us; God be merciful to us ſinners; Lord I am not worthy thou ſhouldeſt come under my roof, &amp;c.</hi> Many other examples might be produced, but theſe may ſuffice to ſhew how unreaſonable your conceit is, that in the Fathers opinion the Bread and Wine were but bare Figures, and did not really con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the very Subſtance of Chriſts Body and Blood.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, my Friend, in the depth of your Solitude and nightly Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions conſiderately think upon the doings of theſe Ancient Fathers. Shall we ſay with Proteſtants, that they <hi>adored</hi> Bread, as the old Ethniques ſaid, that the Chriſtians did eat Mans fleſh at their ſolemn Meetings? which though it were a Calumny, in the ſenſe that the Heathens charged it upon them, yet 'tis certain it took its riſe from the Belief which Chriſtians were known to have concerning the Bleſſed Euchariſt, namely that it was Chriſts Fleſh and Blood in deed and truth, though after a divine and incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manner, and not onely a Figure of them. I told you before, that St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin,</hi> (<hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Confeſs. cap.</hi> 3.) for the nine years in which he was a Manichae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Heretick, confeſſeth of himſelf, that he did nothing but clamour and bark againſt the Church. <hi>But O Lord</hi> (ſaith he, being now converted from that Hereſie) <hi>I finde to my great comfort, that I barked not, all that time, ſo much againſt the Catholick Faith, as againſt certain vain Fancies, which my carnal thoughts and conceptions had fixed to the Faith.</hi> And are not Proteſtants moſt patently guilty of the ſame Phrenſie? Do they any thing elſe, but form to themſelves falſe conceptions of the Doctrine of Catholicks and of the Catholick Church, and then rail at it? But let us pray, that with St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> they may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from this great evil. Let us conſider alſo, whether it be not much more ſafe, to follow the plain words of Chriſt, which ſay, <hi>This is my Body;</hi> and the Univerſal Church, which hath alwayes underſtood thoſe words in their plain and litteral ſenſe: then either the private and contrary expoſitions of Hereticks, or the ſuggeſtion of your own natural ſenſe and reaſon, againſt the words of Chriſt, and againſt the univerſal Belief of his Church, in a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſuch ſublime and high Myſtery; wherein it is far better, and far more agreeable to the humility of Chriſtians, <hi>to captivate our underſtandings</hi> (as the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38261:10"/>Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>to the obedience of Faith.</hi> When we were in the Loins of our firſt Parent <hi>Adam,</hi> we loſt Paradiſe by following our carnal ſenſe and reaſon in the eating of that forbidden Fruit: is it any more then equity then, that upon Gods command, and in full Belief of his Word, we ſhould renounce (as it were) our reaſon for a time, and reſign up our natural underſtandings unto God, to regain Paradiſe? Reflect, I pray, attentively upon thoſe places of the Fathers, which you think make moſt for your opinion, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Symbols of Bread and Wine are but <hi>meer Figures,</hi> and ſee, if they be not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of a fair and reaſonable Interpretation to the contrary, and more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the Catholick Doctrine. In times before any controverſie about the Euchariſt was moved, the Fathers, conſcious to themſelves of their own true ſenſe and meaning, took a liberty of ſpeaking ſometimes, and uttered ſome things in a dubious and ambiguous maner of expreſſion, at leaſt as may ſeem ſo to us, whoſe judgements are for the moſt part byaſſed, &amp; ſet one way more then another, by reaſon of Controverſie. There is ſcarce any Hereſie againſt the Truth of Chriſtian Religion, but if we will be partial Interpreters of the Fathers, we may finde ſome paſſages in them, that through this fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid liberty and ambiguity of ſpeech, may ſeem to favour it. But then let us be ſo equal and indifferent, as to conſider the many and more plain paſſages, which the ſame Fathers, and others contemporary to them, have left us in their writings to the contrary, and in full aſſertion of the Catholick Truth; and our mindes will quickly be ſatisfied: eſpecially if we caſt into the Balance the perpetual practiſe, not onely of the Ancient Fathers themſelves, but even of all the Churches upon Earth, concerning the moſt Bleſſed Sacrament of the Altar.</p>
            <p>Declare therefore, if you can, (for I even challenge you to it) Declare, I ſay, if you can in all your reading, what one Orthodox Father, or any other Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of good name in the Church of God, what one General Council, what one particular Synod, or National Church upon Earth, for the ſpace of 1500. years after Chriſt, did ſo Officiate or celebrate the Holy Euchariſt upon a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as that they held it to be a <hi>meer Figure,</hi> or Sacramental ſign, <hi>onely ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Chriſts Body and Blood unto us, as Proteſtants hold, and not <hi>really being,</hi> or not <hi>really containing,</hi> or not <hi>really exhibiting</hi> and <hi>conveighing</hi> it in <hi>verity and Subſtance</hi> to us; or that they denied the <hi>real Sacrifice</hi> of Chriſts Body in the Euchariſt, upon a true, proper, and real Altar. A Sacrifice, I ſay, in it ſelf, and according to the original Inſtitution thereof, generally Propitiatory for all mankinde, but more particularly effectual for the Church, and thoſe for whom it is ſpecially offered, or that by ſpecial Faith and Devotion do make themſelves capable of the Actual Benefit and Vertue of it.</p>
            <p>But if this be too hard, and cannot be ſhewed, then (becauſe the weal of Eternity is a matter of ſo great conſequence; and this Ordinance of <hi>the daily Sacrifice</hi> a thing of ſo great efficacy and value, that (as Mr. <hi>Aynſworth</hi> notes upon <hi>Levit.</hi> 5.15.) the wiſeſt among the Jews held, that the world did conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue
<pb facs="tcp:38261:11"/>and was upheld by it; and that the general (though not total) aboliſhing thereof amongſt Chriſtians is to be the work of that great enemy of our Lord, (Antichriſt) <hi>Matth</hi> 24.15. <hi>Mark</hi> 13.14. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.27. (according to the judgement and conſent of the Fathers) in conſideration, I ſay, of theſe things, I would gladly have it ſhewen, as well by the Teſtimony of Gods Holy Word, as by the judgement and belief of ſome Orthodox Church, Council, or Synod, within the time above ſpecified, how my poor ſoul may hope to be ſaved, if I leave the univerſal way and rule of all good Chriſtians, which is <hi>Tradition</hi> and <hi>the continued practice</hi> of Chriſts Catholick Church, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the enemies and oppoſers thereof in any of their private and contrary paths.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, becauſe by multitude of words <hi>Truth may be darkened,</hi> Job 38.2. I deſire, that the Anſwer which ſhall be given to theſe demands, may be plain, perſpicuous, and direct to the purpoſe; without evaſions and ſhiftings to any other matter, without any vain and unneceſſary Circumlocutions of words, without Scholaſtical Diſtinctions, or any kinde of that <hi>cunning craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs</hi> of ſpeech and reaſoning, which is contrary to the ſimplicity of true believing, condemned by the Apoſtle <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.14. and fit for nothing, but to abuſe and miſlead ſimple and ſincere mindes into errour: according as in all Ages it may be obſerved to have been the practice of falſe Teachers, and their chief engine, wherewith to entangle and deceive ſouls. The wiſe man doth well deſcribe them, Prov. 2.15. <hi>Their wayes,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>are crooked,— like the way of a Serpent upon a rock,</hi> Prov. 30.19. ever inconſtant and varying, like that of the wanton woman, <hi>who hath forſaken the guide of her youth.</hi> So theſe forſake their Mother the onely True Church of Chriſt; and run gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, every one after their own Fancies and groundleſs Imaginations. But let them wander alone. I deſire, I ſay, that the Anſwer to theſe Queries be punctual and down-right to the matter, that is, having named the Authour, and ſet down his words truly and faithfully, that you uſe no enlargement at all upon them, at leaſt not further then is neceſſary for the clear explication of his meaning, and withal giving your Reaſons in brief. Thus doing, Sir, you ſhall much oblige your faithful Friend, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
